Hi. Good evening everyone. We're going
to get started
now. So, thank you for coming this
evening. My name is Chris Hilditch. I'm
the deputy director of public works for
utilities. So, I deal with the water and
the wastewater treatment plants for the
city of
Lancaster. We're here tonight for our
combined sewer overflow control plan.
This is our second meeting and we'll be
having subsequent meetings as we
continue through the process of
developing a long-term control plan.
So tonight's agenda, we're going to go
over what is a combined
sore. We'll look at our combined sore
overflow efforts to date. We'll talk
about the consent decree that is
requiring us to update our long-term
control plan. This is not our first lawn
control plan. We developed one uh in the
early
1990s, 1998 I should say. And uh this is
the second plan we will be developing
for the city of
Lancaster. We'll look at options for
further reducing our combined sore
overflows. And we'll talk this evening
about the evaluation criteria and the
factors that that affect and influence
the development of a long-term control
plan. We'll talk about next steps and
then at the end of the meeting, we'll
take some questions and comments. will
not be responding to comments this
evening, but we'll be collecting
comments both tonight and what are
available online. We are on uh the
city's YouTube channel tonight, and we
will also be archiving this presentation
on the city's platform for public
engagement called Engage Lancaster. So,
there'll be additional opportunities to
comment this evening. There are some QR
codes in the presentation.
You can access then those later when we
put this presentation
online. So in the city of Lancaster we
have two storm water systems. Two
systems that collect water and waste
water. One is called a combined system.
So that when it rains we're not only
collecting waste water but we're also
collecting storm water. So the areas in
the inner city central the the areas in
the blue green color are where we have
our combined sores and on the pink color
on the outside are our um areas where we
have separate sewers and separate storm
sores. So in a combined system I'm going
to show you a graphic uh in our next
slide. when we have an overflow that
waste water and storm water combines
together and our capacity of sores when
it's exceeded the we will have what's
called a combined sore overflow. So
here's a graphic of our sewer system and
in normal dry weather the waste water
travels down the sewer and then it goes
to the treatment plant. This is just a
schematic. Our treatment plant doesn't
quite look like this, but um we will
direct flow and dry weather directly to
the wastewater treatment plant. But when
it rains and we're collecting any storm
water through the inlets
um that you see in the the city streets,
all that storm water and the wastewater
combined into that same sore, it will
hit a weir when that capacity is
exceeded. It basically overflows into
the overflow
structure. And many older cities have
combined sewers. Locally, city of
Harrisburg has combined sore. City of
Philadelphia, Boston,
um many large urban
cities that have been um I guess in the
business of collecting waste water since
the turn of the century. And our sewers
here in Lancaster um they were built um
late 1800s early 1900s. Um it's a little
hard to see but um the the picture there
is uh one of our from our archives of of
people constructing uh the sore system.
So when you think about it, it's if it
were on the National Historic Register,
it would qualify because it's that old.
It's over a hundred years.
So, these structures, these overflow
structures, we have five of them in the
city. Um, little bit easier to see on
the graphic and after tonight's
presentation, you can look at the the
picture that's on the wall, but our five
locations, we have one up near the Macy
campus on Clay
Street. We have one at Stevens Avenue in
this vicinity. We have two near the
county
park and then one off a new Danville
Pike. Um that's our fifth one. The
picture you see here is not a um is a
picture of our wastewater treatment
plant effluent going into the Knesogga
River. The structure in the foreground
is one of our our clarifiers. You can
see this off of New Dambo Pike. That's
where our wastewater treatment plant is.
And a little close-up view in the next
couple slides. Here's CSO5. Again, Clay
Street. We call that the North
Cso. You can see the old structure was
built near the turn of the century and
still in use
today. All of our overflows are marked
by a graphic telling people that there
is an overflow. And we also have some
CSO warning lights which we tell people,
you know, don't go in the river. There
is a CSO. And that activates um by a
flashing light. It's on for uh 24 hours.
Then it'll blink um blinks red, blinks
red, blinks red, then it blinks yellow.
And then after 24 hours um after the
storm, it will uh turn
green. Here's Stevens Avenue.
Um, Suspahan and Strawberry are right
near the count entrance to the county
park off of Chesapeake
Street. Those are our smallest
CSOs. You can kind of see
the the
um CSO warning light. It's on uh solar
power, so it's always
working. And here's our largest outfall,
Engleside. and that drains a very large
portion of the city and that one is off
New Danville
Pike. So sore overflows can occur 55 to
65 times a year on average. In very wet
years we have more overflows. In dry
years like right now we've been
experiencing a drought. We've had less
overflows. They can last from several
minutes to several hours depending on
the rain event. And if a a rain starts
at quarter of midnight and lasts till
quarter after
midnight, we would have 2 days of CSO
events even though it only occurred for
a half
hour. The majority of our wet weather
flow is treated at the treatment plant.
We have very high swings in flow. On an
average day, we can take uh take in
about 20 million gallons a day of waste
water that we treat. When it rains, we
can go up to 55 60 million gallons a
day. So, very large swings when we have
uh wet weather
events. You can see by the
graphic how much flow is treated and how
much can go out that's not treated.
So what causes our rain our overflows?
It's rainfall. A typical year in our
area is about 40 in. And you can see the
last couple years,
right? Just have the last couple years
shown. 2018 was an extremely wet year.
We had 63 in of rain. So we had a lot of
CSO volume that year as compared to um a
typical year. Now a typical year is an
average. They look at they've looked at
about 60 70 years of rainfall data. And
the typical year for this Cso modeling
is
1962. That's a typical year. But for the
purposes of what I'm going to talk
about, it's it's about 40 inches of
rain.
And in spite of the drought this year,
we have to submit reports to the DP
every year. And one is called the the
chapter 94 report because it comes from
that part of the regulations, the D
regulations. It's chapter
94. We had about 40 ines of rain last
year in 2024 and yet we've had a drought
in 2024, but the first couple months of
the year were really wet. So when you
talk about an average of how much
rainfall we had, we had 40 in a year,
but we are in a drought. And anyone
that's looked at reservoirs or looked at
the level of the Konos Stoa River, it's
much lower. And that that causes causes
us
problems on the water side, on the
drinking water side, but a typical year
is 40 in a
year. So, I told you that this is not
our first long-term control plan that we
had done one in
1998. And since that time, we've done a
lot of work on our CSOS and on our sore
infrastructure. We've been making
improvements at the treatment plant, the
pump stations, and in the collection
system itself. We also do maintenance
items. Okay, everybody's heard of the
city street sweeping, right? get your
car off the the roadway cuz we need to
sweep the streets. Why do we do that?
We're trying to pick up litter, right?
Not everybody is neat, right? Not
everyone takes care of their their trash
and whatever ends up on the street, we
have street sweepers that are sweeping
it up because we don't want it to get
into the sore
system. Those sore grates that we see,
the
inlets, right? When it rains, all of the
debris can get washed in to the sewer
system. So, we have programs where we're
trying to sweep the streets and we send
out crews with big factors. They're like
giant vacuum cleaners to suck the debris
out of the storm drains. So, we do
things like that to make sure that we
can keep debris out of the out of the
waterways. We've installed screens at
Clay Street to catch debris. Those are
before the the cso flow comes out. We
also have a program where we're dealing
with restaurants and educating residents
to control their disposal of fats, oils,
and grease. The acronym there is fog.
That's our fog program. And if you've
been to any of our tableabling events
and mayor's neighborhood week, we'll
have people out there with with magnets
and with little scrapers and, you know,
um trying to educate people to instead
of when you cook your bacon, you don't
pour it down the drain, you pour it in
your trash so you don't clog your own
pipes and you don't clog the cities.
We've done a lot in green
infrastructure.
um just what does green in
infrastructure do? It's soaking up the
storm water and there'll be some slides
on green infrastructure next. And
certainly we're trying to educate
everyone about the csos like in
activities like this evening as well as
educating about litter
prevention. Look at that number, right?
Big number. We've already spent 88
million to reduce CSOS and that's
through infrastructure improvement. It's
from upgrading our wastewater plant,
upgrading our pump stations, increasing
the capacity of those pump stations. So,
we have done a lot over the years to
improve our wastewater
infrastructure. However, there are a lot
of regulations. The EPA has required
communities like ourselves to reduce
those cso overflows into the water
bodies of the United States. So
Lancaster is one of those communities
having CSOS. We ended up with a consent
decree signed in 2017 with the EPA and
the D which required the city to do
more. So, we are now developing that
second long-term control
plan. So, the very general, if you went
and Googled Lancaster consent decree,
you'll find a very multi-page document
with all the requirements that we have
for the CSOS. And over the past couple
years, we've had some major milestones
of modeling the source system,
developing a water quality model. Um
looking at uh ways to control uh csos
called the nine minimum control. So
we've had many many submissions over the
past couple years as we get to tonight,
which is to talk about where we are now,
which in alternatives analysis.
So when we're updating our plan, the
goal is to reduce the frequency of those
cso dischargers within the city's
financial capability. So if we think
about financial capability, it's the
ability to afford the
improvements. The EPA's goals are for us
to demonstrate that water quality
standards will be achieved in the river.
And as I said, we've also had a lot of
obligations in that consent decree over
the over the past couple
years. Water quality standards can be
revised. Longer compliance schedules can
be negotiated so that we can increase
the amount of time that we have to do
cso improvements to again reduce those
overflows. And at the end of the day,
our long-term control plan must be
approved by both the EPA and the DP
because this is a regulatory
requirement. So, our work to date, we've
looked at baseline planning. We've done
a lot of computer modeling to come up
with that typical year and to develop a
model, a computer model that mimics
what's happening in our source system.
We've looked at our planned projects
over the next 30
years. Long time, right? 30 years of
planning. We've looked at different
technologies to find what might work
here. Here in Lancaster, there's a lot
of different technologies that we could
explore. We could explore deep tunnels,
right? Some work that's been done in
Hartford, Connecticut, Providence, Rhode
Island, Boston, Massachusetts. Look up
there. CSO programs. huge
tunnels not always practical in an area
that has a lot of limestone. Okay. So,
what will work here? So, we've looked at
the effectiveness of viable options and
we've se selected some options for
further evaluation. I want to say this
evening I'm not going to get I'm going
to get into an overview of the
technologies but not the specifics. at
our next planning at our next public
meeting, we'll get more into the
specifics.
Okay? So, we're we're trying to do this
over time. So, my goal here, I have a
slide later, is like I will make your
eyes glaze over. Okay? So, I'm trying
not to do that, but I may this
evening. Okay. So, here's our baseline
condition, right? Here's that typical
year, right?
1962 and here's how many overflows we've
had. Okay, so when we looked at our
typical year, when we looked at our
baseline conditions, we looked at
what capital improvements we're going to
use, you can see the difference in where
we are now and where we're driving to
be. Okay. So, a lot of any way you look
at these numbers, we still are going to
have CSOS into the
river. So, now we're going to look at
the options we looked at. And again, the
engineering part where your eyes will
glaze
over. So, I'm going to go over
technologies now.
Okay, one of the things we can do is
upgrade gray infrastructure. So if we
think of concrete, it's gray. In really
simplistic terms, it's something that's
going to involve construction of pump
stations of additional infrastructure at
the plant. More tanks, more pumps. Okay,
this is what we mean by gray
infrastructure. So, as an example, the
picture here is what our north pump
station looks like. It's the largest
pump station in our system and
uh it can pump about uh 30 million
gallons of waste water to the treatment
plant.
Okay? When it rains, we get a lot of
waste
water. It's considered gray
infrastructure.
So one of the things we looked at is
making our pump stations bigger. If we
make our pump stations bigger, we have
to make our force mains bigger and the
cost of those are extremely expensive.
But it was an option we looked
at. We looked at green
infrastructure and I can going to leave
you with the analogy in green
infrastructure. We're trying to soak up
the storm water. We talked about all
that storm water ending up in inlets.
We're trying to stop that from
happening. So, we wanted to soak into
the
ground. In the first picture with the
blackeyed susans, right? You've seen
these throughout the city. These are a
type of bumpout, right? A type of rain
garden. The the plants are rain garden
plants, right? It's a way to collect and
infiltrate
water and make it go into the ground
instead of the sewer system. And these
pumpouts also help us to calm traffic.
People tend to slow down. We hope they
slow down, right? That's another
initiative that the city has with um c
traffic calming. But it's a way to get
the water to soak into the ground. We've
done a lot of tree
plantings. We've we've been encouraging,
you know, residents to take care of
their street
trees. And we've had
a plan called Green It Lancaster. And
again, that's one of those QR codes that
can take you to the plan
later. But the the benefit of green
infrastructure is that we're keeping
that water out of the source system.
We're allowing to it to infiltrate and
sometimes underneath the ground we have
what's called infiltration beds. So it's
allowed to infiltrate through like
porous pavements. We have some porest
pavements on Malberry Street and if
you've ever been to Brandon Park and
looked at the basketball courts there,
those are also porous asphalt. So these
are ways that we can get the water into
the ground and let it seep into the
ground rather than the being directed
into the source system. So some pictures
there of poor porest pavements and of
course the picture in the middle
planting a tree. As a tree will grow and
that root systems there it will also
help to pull water into its root system
instead of again the water going into
the source
system. We can store excess flow.
We're looking at storing some flow under
the Macy soccer fields. We've about five
acres and this flow flow would be
captured in a tank constructed below
ground. And again, we're retaining that
excess storm water flow so that it
doesn't go into the treatment plant when
it rains. We can pump it in there later
and dry weather flow.
We're looking at separating source in
key areas of the system. Some are listed
there on the right hand side. We're
looking at separating storm water flow
from the sanitary flow by constructing
new sanitary or storm
source and some of those sort
separations especially in the area here
in Duke Street right in the area we're
in now. If we can separate some of the
sores in this area, we can reduce the
csos at the county park at Susuana and
Strawberry
CSOS. We looked at maximizing flow to
the treatment plant. We've already done
some of those projects by increasing the
capacity of pumping at our north pump
station, but we also looked at some
additional improvements that we can
implement to increase
capacity. So, what did we end up with?
We're going to look at the gray
infrastructure, the green
infrastructure, storage, source
separation, and maximizing flow to the
treatment plant. There's a lot of things
that we evaluated that didn't make the
cut, right? I mentioned the deep
tunnels. That's something that we
evaluated, but the costs were so high,
it was something we that was dismissed
during the analysis. as an example.
So I mentioned that we had already
planned projects over the next 30 years
and we looked at Cso
projects.
And as we summed up the projects and
looked at the different basins and the
basins are named on the left side of the
screen, right? North Stevens, Susuana,
Strawberry, and Engleside. Those are the
basins we looked at. We can see as a
baseline what we have with after all our
projects are done and as we make
investments in the system how we can
drive the csos the number of events
down.
Okay. If we spent millions and millions
and millions and millions of dollars,
right, much in excess of that 73 million
investment that's shown in the last
column, we might get these down, right?
But remember, I talked about spending to
the limits of our
affordability. Spending to the limits of
our
affordability. And you can see with you
know the minimum investment here of 30
million we can reduce especially in
Engleside our cso events but they're not
going to go down to
zero at our larger cso
locations.
Okay. So a lot of options and now we're
going to talk about the next steps. How
do we select the best options for the
city of
Lancaster? We looked at several
criteria regulatory
compliance. So remember I said that this
is directed by the
EPA and the DP. So we do have a
regulatory requirement to to do this
plan as well as to do our best within
the limits of our affordability to
reduce our
CSOS. So we look at cso
performance. How often do the csos
occur?
Right? 30 in a year, 50 in a year. The
frequency, how
many? And then we also can look at the
wet weather volume
capture. I can still have a cso
event but less will overflow. So less
gets into the river. So frequency how
many times it happens and the volume of
capture how much can I keep right how
can I much can I infiltrate into the
ground or still treat at the wastewater
plant.
What drives regulatory
compliance are the water quality
standards. These are set by the EPA and
the
DP. The ones we look at are bacteria.
They affect recreation, right? No one
wants to swim in a river or kayak or
wade, right? However, we want to use the
river. We don't want to swim in
bacteria. We don't want to swim in
wastewater.
The rivers are there for aquatic life,
right? The fish have to survive. The
salamanders have to survive, right? The
national salamander for or the state
salamander, the hellbender, right? It
needs to survive, right? So the concern
is dissolved oxygen, suspended solids,
ammonia, what we
discharge from the wastewater treatment
plant and
floatables, debris, right? No one wants
to see pieces of toilet paper going down
the river. So our efforts are always to
capture and to screen. We want to avoid
any of these issues. So this is why
we're trying to do a CS. to wait or I
shouldn't say do but continue to do.
Right? Again, this is our second
long-term control
plan. So, we can look at water quality.
We've developed a water quality model to
show the impacts on the CSOS on the
Konosoga River. So, we look at how does
dissolved oxygen change, what does the
effect of solids
have. It can predict, this model can
predict the water quality
improvements. But we also have to
acknowledge that the Konosoga River is
heavily impacted above the city limits.
Okay? Heavily impacted from non-point
source solution pollution, you know,
from farming, from agricultural runoff.
And if you want to learn more about the
background of the river, there's another
QR code that you can learn more about
the impact of the upstream
conditions. So we looked at
constructability. Remember those
tunnels? Could we construct those
tunnels? So we have to look at
constructibility, the available
availability of land. How complex is it
to do the
construction and whether that new
infrastructure can be easily
maintained. Okay, this is an overview of
our wastewater plant. Right. So, we
looked at how we could expand that
plant. Right? We're constrained by the
land too. So, our site there can only
accommodate so much
uh additional infrastructure.
We looked at the community
objectives, our future Lancaster, the
comprehensive plan, right? That was
developed as a framework for what the
community wanted and what was important
to to to the community to Lancaster
City.
So maintaining the quality of life is
important from a cso perspective.
Reducing bacteria which hampers
recreational use of the Konosoga River
is
important and we are upstream of the
Chesapeake Bay. Right. Kanesoga
discharges into the Suscuana and the
Suscuana goes into the Chesapeake Bay
and certainly the Chesapeake Bay has
been studied for many years on the
impacts of nutrients and sediments. So
those of us that are all upstream of the
Chesapeake Bay, we're doing our part to
what we discharge into the what our
wastewater plant discharges is in
compliance with all of those standards.
And
last we looked at
cost and we'll develop met metrics on
what's the cost per gallon captured.
Right? So we want you've heard the
phrase right more bang for your buck. So
we want to be able to choose options
that gives us the best return on our
investment. you know the capital cost,
the future operation and maintenance
cost and nothing lasts forever. So the
refer future replacement cost because
everything we do in infrastructure has a
finite life,
right? Your car engine has a finite
life, your roof has a finite life. Well,
so does our
infrastructure. But I will say one
thing, we've gotten our money out of our
combined source system, right? Remember
I said it was built in the turn of the
century and we're still using
it. But we have to look at the
customer's ability to pay. So that's up
next. One of the things that is required
as a submission to the EPA and D is
what's called a financial capability
analysis. So everything has an acronym.
So that's the FCA, the financial
capability analysis.
And that looks at that overall ability
to pay, right? What's the impact
on a typical residential
customer? So if we go out 30 years,
we've gone out 30 years and we look at a
snapshot, so it's only a point in time
of what the residential indicator is for
a resident paying a sewer bill and a
storm water bill. Okay, all those
improvements over 30
years and EPA looks at if we look at the
far right hand the side side of the
screen you can see low
burden, medium range burden and high
burden. So if we look at what the
percentage of that typical Whoops, sorry
about that. what a typical soore and
storm water bill is as a
percentage of an average income. Median
income. Median income. We have what's
called the residential
indicator. So it's a percentage of the
city's median income. So what's a median
income?
Right? If I have five
numbers, 1 2 3 4 5, right? We can add
all those up and we can get an average.
But a median,
right, would be the gentleman in the
blue shirt, right? If I have five people
with two on either side, he would be the
median. Okay? So, if we ranked all of
the incomes throughout the whole city,
that's what we're comparing it to. And
we get these numbers from the census
data. Okay? So, if we look at those
costs against the median income, and
we've done 30 years worth of
improvements, about
2.26% of that median income is going to
be used to pay a sewer and a storm water
bill. So, in the EPA's metric, that
would be a high burden, right?
2.26%. Right? That's our baseline.
And then as you see the percentages
increase, remember I said those little
buckets of projects, 30 million, 51
million, 63 million, 73 million. As we
add a number of projects, you can see
that percentage, that residential
indicator against the median income and
what the sore bill would be, it goes up.
So what will end up being negotiated
with EPA is how long do we have to
implement improvements to reduce the
CSOS and how long right how long that
will take and how much they will require
us to
spend and that all has to be
negotiated. So it takes a long time.
It's been a long time, right? We've been
at this since
2017 through all these analysis and we
have a lot longer time to
go because all of this again will have
to be negotiated.
So what also influences right it's not
all about just the
csos we have critical infrastructure
that we're already maintaining and that
we need to see being able to you be used
by future
generations our drinking water systems
the wastewater system and the storm
water systems which we talked about
tonight. The city has to be able to
continue to invest and maintain that
critical
infrastructure. There's a lot of
regulatory
compliance in sore we talked about
tonight, but we could have another
public meeting and we can talk about
water and at some point we'll have one
of
those. We have to be able to meet all of
the new requirements.
We've been bombarding the citizens, the
customers of our water plant. Please
take a picture of your water source,
water service line. Right? That's going
to continue. We've got to get an
inventory of our water service
lines. Many of you, you're all water
customers. You've received letters,
right, that there's POA in the water.
There's POA in the water, right? Anybody
have a waterproof jacket on
tonight? Do you
do you have POA
too? Make brownies and a cake
mix, right? Easy to get out of the cake
mix. Flows real nice to get out of the
package.
Pifoa firefighting foam.
A lot of today's
inconveniences have resulted in
pollutants that now water has to take
care of.
Right? Water is not a poller. Right? We
we view ourselves as giving something
life
sustaining and yet manufacturers of
chemicals over the years have developed
something that now has been deemed a
problem.
So, we have to spend money on
water. We're spending money on the
Chesapeake, right? Chesapeake Bay
initiatives, all of the policies, right?
We want a good future for ourselves, for
our children, for our grandchildren, for
the next
generation. So, we have a comprehensive
plan that guides that, our future
Lancaster. And we have to be able to
afford it.
So, when we start developing our
preferred alternatives, that'll be the
next public
meeting. All of these factors will
influence the long-term control
plan, and we're going to try to choose
the
best that we can for the city of
Lancaster.
So in
summary, the EPA and the D are requiring
that we reduce our CSOS, right? We're
not going to be able to do nothing, but
we recognize that those cso reduction is
going to
cost
money. The actions and the time frames
of when we implement these projects,
it's going to depend on that cost
burden, right? that financial capability
analysis, what can our customers
afford? And that burden will be analyzed
using a cost analysis that the EPA
requires under the consent decree.
Right? That's that financial capability
analysis. But at the
end, that's a really important last
statement.
We're doing our part to reduce the
csos, but the cssos their
impact have only a little impact on the
overall water quality in the Konesoga
River because of upstream
conditions. Okay. So, we'll do our
part, but we'll still have issues with
the Konos Stoa River.
I thank you for your attention
tonight. Um, please write down your
questions. If anyone wants to to say
anything or make any statements or talk
about any questions, um, we'd be happy
to do that. And for those of you joining
remotely, thank you for your attention.
And I'll be signing off now. Thank you.
Oh, that's our QR code. And if you also
Google engage Lancaster,
um you can get to
um the page that we're
on. One more slide. Yeah, I I got it.
One more slide. One more
slide. And here's our email
address. ltcp comments at
cityoflancasterpa.gov.
Okay, I'll wait a minute so you can take
that. For those of you in the audience,
ltcp
comments at cityoflancasterpa.gov.